## Yen-Hsun Lin

#### Curriculum Vitae

Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica No. 128, Section 2 Academia Road Nangang District, Taipei City, 115, Taiwan yenhsun@phys.ncku.edu.tw

**\** +886-2-2789 8387

**1** 0000-0001-7911-7591

yenhsunlin.github.io

### RESEARCH SUMMARY

I am an astroparticle physicist with expertise in multimessenger astronomy and dark matter (DM) detection. My research focuses on three key areas: (1) supernova-neutrino-boosted DM, (2) anomalous heating from DM in compact stars, and (3) probing DM self-interactions and DM-nucleon interactions in stars and planets. The first area is particularly vital as it opens the new possibility for direct DM mass measurements using time-of-flight techniques. I also collaborate with DUNE/COHERENT members and work on reducing systematic uncertainties in DUNE-like detectors. Additionally, I contributed to the JUNO collaboration, assessing its data analysis to solar-captured DM. My background in astroparticle physics and extensive research experience have provided me with a deep understanding of DM and its broader implications to our Universe.

#### Topic of Interest

Astroparticle physics, dark matter physics, supernova and compact star physics, high performance computation, Bayesian inference, and Monte Carlo simulation.

#### **Programming**

Python, Cython, C++, Mathematica and Matlab.

#### **EDUCATION**

National Chiao Tung University

Hsinchu, Taiwan Aug. 2011 – Jul. 2016

PhD of the Institute of Physics

Thesis: Indirect detection of dark matter through neutrinos

**Advisor:** Prof. Guey-Lin Lin

National Chiao Tung University

Hsinchu, Taiwan

Master of the Institute of Physics (direct to PhD program)

Aug. 2010 – Jul. 2011

Advisor: Prof. Guey-Lin Lin

National Chiao Tung University

Hsinchu, Taiwan

Bachelor of the Department of Electrophysics

Aug. 2006 – Jul. 2010

### **EXPERIENCE**

Postdoctoral Scholar

Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica

Taipei, Taiwan

Aug. 2023 – Present

Host: Dr. Meng-Ru Wu

Visiting Scholar Melbourne, Australia School of Physics, Melbourne University Oct. 2023 – Nov. 2023

Host: Prof. Nicole F. Bell

Postdoctoral Scholar

Physics Division, National Center for Theoretical Sciences

Taipei, Taiwan

Dec. 2021 – Jul. 2023

Distinguished Postdoctoral Scholar

Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica

Taipei, Taiwan

Aug. 2019 – Dec. 2021

Host: Dr. Meng-Ru Wu

Postdoctoral Researcher

Department of Physics, National Cheng Kung University

Tainan, Taiwan
Oct. 2017 – Jul. 2019

Host: Prof. Chuan-Hung Chen

### Honors & Awards

1. NCTS Postdoc Paper Award

Awarded by the Physics Division, National Center for Theoretical Sciences (NCTS).

2. Best Research Paper Award for Junior Research Investigator
Awarded by the Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica.

Taiwan, 2024

3. Selected Participant of the 13<sup>th</sup> HOPE Meeting with Nobel Laureates
Representative of Taiwan.

Japan, 2022

4. Distinguished Postdoctoral Scholar
Independent position with grant, selected by the Academia Sinica.

Taiwan, 2019

5. **Annual Best PhD Thesis in Physical Science**Best PhD Thesis of the year, awarded by the Taiwan Physical Society.

Taiwan, 2017

6. Selected Honorary Member of the Phi Tau Phi Scholastic Society
Issued to the student graduated with top score.

Taiwan, 2016

# COLLABORATION MEMBERSHIP

1. With Members of DUNE/COHERENT Collaborations USA

♦ Collaborating with Dr. Gianluca Petrillo and Dr. Yun-Tse Tsai 2020 – Present

 $\diamond$  Analysis the impact due to  $\nu_e$ -Ar cross section uncertainty

♦ Improving pinched parameter sensitivity via Machine Learning

♦ Sensitivity projection for the solar-captured DM in JUNO

### **ADVISEES**

#### PhD students

1. Vo Quang Nhat

Hsinchu, Taiwna

Institute of Physics, NYCU

Aug. 2022 – Jul. 2023

Co-supervising with Prof. Guey-Lin Lin

2. Lam Thi To Uyen

Hsinchu, Taiwna

Institute of Physics, NYCU

Aug. 2022 – Jul. 2023

Co-supervising with Prof. Guey-Lin Lin

#### Undergraduates

1. Tsung-Han Tsai (ASIoP Summer Student Program)

Hsinchu, Taiwna

Department of Physics, NTHU

Jul. 2022 - Aug. 2022

Co-supervising with Dr. Meng-Ru Wu and work published in *Phys. Rev. D* **108**, 083013 (2023). Currently a master student in NTHU.

2. Yong Sheng Yap (ASIoP Summer Student Program)

Hsinchu, Taiwna

Department of Physics, NTHU

Jul. 2021 - Aug. 2021

Co-supervising with Dr. Meng-Ru Wu and currently a PhD student in Cambridge University (UK).

3. Wen-Hua Wu (ASIoP Summer Student Program)

Taipei, Taiwna

Department of Physics, NTU

Jul. 2020 - Aug. 2020

Co-supervising with Dr. Meng-Ru Wu and work published in *Phys. Rev. Lett.* **130**, 111002 (2023). Currently a PhD student in Rice University (USA).

4. Adeela Malik (SLAC Summer Student Program)

San Antonio, USA

Department of Physics, University of Texas at San Antonio

Jul. 2020 – Aug. 2020

Co-supervising with and Prof. Hirohisa Tanaka (SLAC) and Dr. Yun-Tse Tsai (SLAC).

#### GITHUB REPOSITORIES

ullet snorer: Spernova-Neutrino-bOosted daRk mattER

**Description:** Evaluating the time-of-flight signatures of boosted dark matter due to supernova neutrinos from Milky Way, SN1987a and arbitrary distant galaxy.

Role: Main developer and maintainer

Project Page: https://github.com/yenhsunlin/snorer

• dukes: DiffU se-boosted darK mattEr by S upernova neutrinos

**Description:** Evaluating the signatures of diffuse boosted dark matter by supernova neutrinos in the early Universe.

Role: Main developer and maintainer

Project Page: https://github.com/yenhsunlin/dukes

• dynesor: DYnamical NEsted Sampling integrat OR

**Description:** MCMC integrator for evaluating multidimensional integration based on dynamical

nested sampling.

Role: Main developer and maintainer

Project Page: Non-disclose.

# SCIENTIFIC ACTIVITIES & SERVICES

### Workshop organization

• Organizer of the Mini-workshop on Novel Experimental and Astrophysical Probes for Dark Matter, Taipei, Taiwan, 2021

#### Journal referee

- 1. Physical Letter B
- 2. Annals of Physics

### Publication List

### REFEREED ARTICLES

Dagger (†) and asterisk (\*) indicate first author and corresponding author, respectively. Otherwise, the author list is arranged alphabetically.

- 1. Y.-H. Lin<sup>†,\*</sup> and M.-R. Wu, Supernova-neutrino-boosted dark matter from all galaxies, Phys. Rev. Lett. 133, 111004 (2024) [arXiv:2404.08528]
- 2. Y.-H. Lin<sup>†,\*</sup>, T.-H. Tsai, G.-L. Lin, H. T.-K. Wong and M.-R. Wu, Signatures of afterglows from light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos in current and future large underground detectors, Phys. Rev. D 108, 083013 (2023) [arXiv:2307.03522]
- 3. Y.-H. Lin<sup>†,\*</sup>, W.-H. Wu, M.-R. Wu and H. T.-K. Wong, Searching for afterglow: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos, Phys. Rev. Lett 130, 111002 (2023) [arXiv:2206.06864]
- 4. A. Bauswein, G. Guo, J.-H. Lien, Y.-H. Lin and M.-R. Wu, Compact dark objects in neutron star mergers, Phys. Rev. D 107, 083002 (2023) [arXiv:2012.11908]
- 5. G.-L. Lin and Y.-H. Lin\*, Exploring dark sector parameters in light of neutron star temperatures, Phys. Rev. D 104, 063021 (2021) [arXiv:2102.11151]
- 6. G.-L. Lin and Y.-H. Lin\*, Analysis on the black hole formations inside old neutron stars by isospin-violating dark matter with self-interaction, JCAP 08, 022 (2020) [arXiv:2004.05312]
- 7. C.-S. Chen and Y.-H. Lin\*, Reheating neutron stars with the annihilation of self-interacting dark matter, JHEP 08, 069 (2018) [arXiv:1804.03409]
- 8. C.-S. Chen and Y.-H. Lin\*, On the evolution process of two-component dark matter in the Sun, JHEP 04, 074 (2018) [arXiv:1802.06956]
- 9. C.-H. Chen and Y.-H. Lin, Study of  $B_c^{\pm} \to (D^0 K^{\pm}, D^0 \pi^{\pm})$  decays, arXiv:1710.05531
- 10. C.-S. Chen, G.-L. Lin, Y.-H. Lin and F. Xu, The 17 MeV anomaly in beryllium decays and U(1) portal to dark matter, Int. J. Mod. Phys. A 32, 1750178 (2017) [arXiv:1609.07198]
- 11. C.-S. Chen, G.-L. Lin and Y.-H. Lin, Thermal transport of the solar captured dark matter and its impact on the indirect dark matter search, Phys. Dark Univ. 14, 35 (2016) [arXiv:1508.05263]
- 12. F. An et al. [JUNO Collaboration], Neutrino Physics with JUNO, J. Phys. G 43, 1 (2016) [arXiv:1507.05613]

- 13. C.-S. Chen, G.-L. Lin and Y.-H. Lin, Complementary test of the dark matter self-interaction by direct and indirect detections, JCAP 01, 013 (2016) [arXiv:1505.03781]
- 14. Z. Djurcic et al. [JUNO Collaboration], JUNO conceptual design report, arXiv:1508.07166
- 15. G.-L. Lin, **Y.-H. Lin** and F.-F. Lee, Probing the coupling of heavy dark matter to nucleons by detecting neutrino signature from the Earth core, Phys. Rev. D **91**, 033002 (2015) [arXiv:1409.3094]
- 16. C.-S. Chen, F.-F. Lee, G.-L. Lin and **Y.-H. Lin**, Probing dark matter self-interaction in the Sun with IceCube-PINGU, JCAP 10, 049 (2014) [arXiv:1408.5471]

### Conference Proceedings

- 1. G.-L. Lin and **Y.-H. Lin**, Exploring dark sector parameters in light of neutron star temperatures, PoS ICHEP2022 106 (2022)
- 2. Lam T. T. Uyen, G.-L. Lin and Y.-H. Lin, Constraints on lepton-flavor-violating scalar portal using the Belle II result in the search for  $e^+e^- \rightarrow e^{\pm}+invisible$  with L=276 pb<sup>-1</sup>, PoS ICHEP2022 1229 (2022)
- 3. Y.-H. Lin and G.-L. Lin, Analysis on the black hole formations inside old neutron stars by isospin-violating dark matter with self-interaction, PoS ICHEP2020 598 (2020)
- 4. Y.-H. Lin and G.-L. Lin, Probing self-interacting dark matter through neutron stars, PoS EPS-HEP2019 075 (2020)
- 5. C.-S. Chen, G.-L. Lin Y.-H. Lin and F. Xu, The 17 MeV anomaly in beryllium decays and U(1) portal to dark matter, PoS EPS-HEP2017 627 (2017)
- 6. C.-S. Chen, **Y.-H. Lin** and G.-L. Lin, Complementary test of the dark matter self-interaction in dark U(1) model by direct and indirect detection, JPS Conf. Proc. **14**, 020103 (2017)
- 7. Y.-H. Lin, C.-S. Chen and G.-L. Lin, Thermal transport of the solar captured dark matter and its implication, JPS Conf. Proc. 14, 020110 (2017)
- 8. C.-S. Chen, G.-L. Lin and Y.-H. Lin, Probing dark matter self-interaction in the Sun with IceCube-PINGU, PoS FPC2015, 065 (2015)
- 9. Y.-H. Lin, C.-S. Chen and G.-L. Lin, Thermal transport of the solar captured dark matter and its implication, PoS EPS-HEP2015, 385 (2015)
- 10. C.-S. Chen, F.-F. Lee, G.-L. Lin and Y.-H. Lin, The dark matter self-interaction and its impact on the critical mass for dark matter evaporations inside the Sun, Nucl. Part. Phys. Proc. 273-252, 347-375 (2016)

### **Presentations**

# INVITED CONFERENCE/WORKSHOP TALKS

- Detection of SNν BDM in current and future large underground detectors
   The 3<sup>rd</sup> International Joint Workshop on the Standard Model and Beyond and the 11<sup>th</sup> KIAS Workshop on Particle Physics and Cosmology, Jeju, Korea (2023/11)
- Searching for afterglow: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos
   Interplay of Nuclear, Neutrino and BSM Physics at Low-Energies (INT 23–85w), Seattle, USA (2023/4)
- 3. Light DM constraints from neutron stars and supernova neutrinos
  Theory Meets Experiment: Particle Physics and Cosmology, Quy Nhon, Vietnam (2023/1)
- 4. Light DM constraints from neutron stars and supernova neutrinos NCTS Annual Theory Meeting, Taipei, Taiwan (2022/12)
- Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos
   Dark Matter in Compact Objects, Stars, and in Low Energy Experiments (INT 22–2b), Seattle, USA (2022/8)
- 6. Searching the afterglow from supernova neutrino boosted dark matter Particle Physics Phenomenology Workshop (PPP 14), Taipei, Taiwan (2022/6)
- 7. Exploring dark matter with compact stars Mini-workshop on Novel Experimental and Astrophysical Probes for Dark Matter, Taipei, Taiwan (2021/3)
- 8. Probing the isospin violation of self-interacting dark matter through old neutron stars NCTS Annual Theory Meeting, Taipei, Taiwan (2019/12)
- 9. Probing self-interacting dark matter through neutron stars
  Particle Physics Phenomenology Workshop (PPP 13), Taipei, Taiwan (2019/6)

# CONTRIBUTED CONFERENCE/WORKSHOP TALKS

1. Searching light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos in Super-K, Hyper-K and DUNE International Conference on Topics in Astroparticle and Underground Physics (TAUP 2023), Vienna, Austria (2023/8)

- 2. Detection of afterglows from supernova-neutrino boosted dark matter in large underground detectors
  - International Summer Institute on Phenomenology of Elementary Particle Physics and Cosmology, Nantou, Taiwan (2023/8)
- 3. Analysis on the black hole formations inside old neutron stars by isospin-violating dark matter with self-interaction
  - International Conference on High Energy Physics (ICHEP 2022), Prague, Czechia (2020/8)
- 4. The art of inference: Practicing Bayesian reasoning in computer vision problems PyCon TW, Taipei, Taiwan (2019/9)
- Probing self-interacting dark matter through neutron stars
   European Physical Society Conference on High Energy Physics (EPS-HEP 2019), Ghent,
   Belgium (2019/7)
- On the evolution process of two-component dark matter in the Sun International Conference on Neutrino Physics and Astrophysics (Neutrino 2018), Heidelberg, Germany (2018/6)
- 7. Thermal transport of the solar captured dark matter and its implication International Symposium on Nuclei in the Cosmos (NIC-XIV), Niigata, Japan (2016/6)
- 8. Thermal transport of the solar captured dark matter and its implication European Physical Society Conference on High Energy Physics (EPS-HEP 2015), Vienna, Austria (2015/7)
- The dark matter self-interaction and its impact on the critical mass for dark matter evaporations inside the Sun International Conference on High Energy Physics (ICHEP 2014), Valéncia, Spain (2014/7)
- Probing the coupling of heavy dark matter to nucleons by detecting neutrino signature from the Earth core
   International Symposium on Particles, Strings and Cosmology (PASCOS 2014), Taipei, Taiwan (2013/12)
- Probing the coupling of heavy dark matter to nucleons by detecting neutrino signature from the Earth core
   International Symposium on Cosmology and Particle Astrophysics (CosPA 2013), Honolulu, Hawaii (2013/6)

# SEMINARS & COLLOQUIA

- 1. Behind the veil of darkness: A journey into the Uncharted Universe
  Colloquium for the Department of Physics, Tunghai University, Taichung, Taiwan (2024/5)
- 2. Exploring light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos in the present and past Universe Seminar for the Department of Physics, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu, Taiwan (2024/5)

- 3. Search for afterglow: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrino
  Seminar for the Department of Physics, National Tsing Hua University, Hsinchu, Taiwan
  (2023/5)
- 4. Search for afterglow: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrino
  Seminar for the Department of Physics, Chung Yuan Christian University, Taoyuan, Taiwan
  (2023/3)
- 5. Search for afterglow: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrino Webinar for the SNEWS Institution, USA (2023/2)
- 6. Search for afterglow: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrino
  Seminar for the Department of Physics, National Taiwan Normal University, Taipei, Taiwan
  (2022/11)
- 7. Searching for afterglow: Light dark matter boosted by supernova neutrinos NCTS Particle Physics Journal Club, National Taiwan University, Taipei, Taiwan (2022/9)
- 8. Searching light to heavy dark matter by supernova neutrinos and neutron star temperature Webinar for the University of New South Wales Sydney and University of Sydney (Sydney-CPPC), Sydney, Australia (2021/10)
- 9. Probing dark matter with neutron star
  Seminar for the Department of Physics, Chung Yuan Christian University, Taoyuan, Taiwan
  (2020/11)
- 10. Probing dark matter with neutron star Seminar for the Center of Astrophysics and Gravity, National Taiwan Normal University, Taipei, Taiwan (2020/7)
- 11. Neutron star sensitivity on isospin-violating dark matter with self-interaction Seminar for the Department of Physics, National Central University, Taoyuan, Taiwan (2020/6)
- 12. Uncharted Universe
  Colloquium for the Department of Physics, Tamkang University, New Taipei, Taiwan (2018/12)
- 13. Reheating neutron stars with the annihilation of self-interacting dark matter.

  Seminar for the Institute of Physics, National Chiao Tung University, Hsinchu, Taiwan (2018/5)
- 14. Reheating neutron stars with the annihilation of self-interacting dark matter. Seminar for the Institute of Physics, Academia Sinica, Taipei, Taiwan (2018/4)
- 15. Indirect detection of dark matter through neutrinos
  Seminar for the Department of Physics, Chung Yuan Christian University, Taoyuan, Taiwan
  (2017/12)